Guide to the John W. Clark, Jr. Bioengineering Department records UA 412
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
John W. Clark, Jr. Bioengineering Department records
1989-2011
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Clark, John W., Jr., 1936-2017
UA 412
0.5 Linear Feet 1 box
The collection consists of materials from Dr. John W. Clark, Jr., professor in both the Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering and the Department of Bioengineering at Rice University. The collection also includes records of Dr. Clark's participation in the work of several university committees, specifically Parking, Graduate Student, Admissions, and the Library. In addition there is material prepared for evaluation of courses to determine ABET accreditation in 2005.
Biographical / Historical
John W. Clark, Jr. was born December 24, 1936, in Rochester, New York. Before embarking on his bachelor of science degree in electrical engineering at Christian Brothers College in Memphis, Tennessee, he served for three years in the U.S Marine Corps. He began his graduate work at Case Institute of Technology, earning an M.S. in electrical engineering in 1965, followed by a Ph.D. in engineering at Case Western Reserve University in 1967.
He served as a Research Associate at Case Western Reserve in 1967-68 and then in 1968 was appointed an Assistant Professor at Rice University in the Department of Electrical Engineering. He advanced through the ranks at Rice, becoming a full professor in 1979. While teaching and supervising graduate theses, he conducted research in neural and cardiac electrophysiology, mathematical modeling of biological systems, applying signal processing methods to biological systems, nonlinear system dynamics, and electromagnetic field theory.
In 1989 Dr. Clark initiated discussion with five Rice colleagues, in chemical engineering, mechanical engineering and materials sciences, biology, physics, and biochemistry, and a representative of Baylor College of Medicine, on the formation of an interdepartmental program, which became the Department of Bioengineering. In 1992 he received the Distinguished Service Award of the Houston Society for Engineering in Medicine and Biology, and in 1993 he became a Founding Fellow of the American Institute of Engineering in Medicine and Biology at the National Academy of Sciences. In 2005 he was elected a Fellow by the Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers.
At the time of his death at 80 in August 2017, Dr. Clark held professorships in both the Electrical and Computer Engineering Department and the Bioengineering Department in his forty-ninth year of teaching at Rice.
Content Description
The collection consists of materials from the career at Rice University of Dr. John W. Clark, Jr., professor in both the Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering and the Department of Bioengineering. He was instrumental in the founding of the latter; thus the collection includes records of the development of its curriculum from 1989 through 1997. The collection also includes records of Dr. Clark's participation in the work of several university committees, specifically Parking, Graduate Student, Admissions, and the Library. In addition there is material prepared for evaluation of courses to determine ABET accreditation in 2005.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored onsite at the Woodson Research Center.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred to the Woodson Research Center via Melissa Kean.
Index Terms
Subjects
bioengineering
Document Types
annual reports; minutes (administrative records); letters (correspondence)
Subjects (Corporations)
Rice University
- Series I: Clark files
  - Curriculum Vitae (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bioengineering Program at Rice, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bioengineering Educational Program, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bioengineering Department, 1993-1997 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Proposed Curriculum in Bioengineering, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bioinformatics, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Annual Report data, 1987-1992 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Dean's Report, 1998-07 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Whitaker talk, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Appointments, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Syd Lamb (re: Cognitive Neuroscience) (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Parking Committee, 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Graduate Student Committee, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Admissions Committee, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - ABET Accreditation, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Library FY2011 – John Hunter (Box 1, Folder 16)